<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mans fury subservient to Gods glory. A sermon preached to the Parliament at Margarets Westminster Febr. 20. 1656. it being a day of publick thanksgiving. With the addition of an applicatory discourse about the mutuall animosities of Christians, which was omitted for want of time when the sermon was delivered. By John Warren, M.A. minister of the gospel at Hatfield Broad-oak in Essex.</title>
            <author>Warren, John, minister of Hatfield Broad Oak, Essex.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97221</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W974</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E916_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207491</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99858759</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99858759</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110817</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97221)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110817)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 138:E916[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mans fury subservient to Gods glory. A sermon preached to the Parliament at Margarets Westminster Febr. 20. 1656. it being a day of publick thanksgiving. With the addition of an applicatory discourse about the mutuall animosities of Christians, which was omitted for want of time when the sermon was delivered. By John Warren, M.A. minister of the gospel at Hatfield Broad-oak in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Warren, John, minister of Hatfield Broad Oak, Essex.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 34, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.G. for Nathanael Webb and William Grantham, at the black Bear in Paul's Church-yard, near the little North door,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an order to print on the final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 6".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110817:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MANS FURY SUBSERVIENT TO GODS GLORY.</p>
            <p>A SERMON preached to the <hi>Parliament</hi> at <hi>Margarets Weſtminſter</hi> Febr. 20. 1656. it being a day of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Thankſgiving.</p>
            <p>WITH The Addition of an Applicatory Diſcourſe about the Mutuall Animoſities of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, which was omitted for want of time when the Sermon was delivered.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN WARREN,</hi> M. A. Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Hatfield Broad-oak</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>J.G.</hi> for <hi>Nathanael Webb</hi> and <hi>William Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham,</hi> at the black Bear in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, near the little North door. 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:110817:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110817:2"/>
            <head>CELSISSIMO, HONORATISSIMO<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> SENATUI, TOTIUS</head>
            <p>ANGLIAE, SCOTIAE, ET HIBERNIAE, IN PUBLICIS CONCILIIS RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PRAESENTATIVO, CONCIO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NEM HANC QUALEM QUALEM NUPER APUD EUNDEM HABITAM IN HUMILLIMAE OBSERVANTIAE ET OFFICII MONUMENTUM</p>
            <closer>D.D.D.
<signed>
                  <hi>Servorum Chriſti Minimus,</hi> JOHANNES VVARREN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:110817:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110817:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the <hi>PARLIAMENT,</hi> FEBRUARY 20. It being a Day of THANKSGIVING.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 76.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Surely the wrath of man ſhall praiſe thee, the remainder of wrath wilt thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Pſalm is for the day, <hi>Euchariſticall,</hi> a Pſalm of Praiſe, and hath, as many learned men conceive, a <hi>Propheticall</hi> Reſpect to the great Deliverance of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> from the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Army, and the miraculous Deſtruction of that Adverſary by the hand of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, of which we read 2 <hi>King.</hi> 19.35. Indeed ſome paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110817:4"/> in the Pſalm ſeem to look a little that way,<note place="margin">Non eſt ut pro certâ aliquâ hiſtoriâ aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandâ ad quam hic pſalmus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiciat, anxiè laboremus. <hi>Muſcul.</hi>
               </note> and the Septuagint have added to the title theſe words, [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] a Song againſt the <hi>Aſſyyrian;</hi> which 'tis like hath carried ſome Interpreters: But whether the Pſalm were calculated purpoſely for that point in the circle of Providence or no (a queſtion in which I labour not) it may ſerve indifferently for the uſe and comfort of the people of God in all ages upon all rejoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing occaſions, eſpecially ſuch as reſpect their preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation againſt their enemies.</p>
            <p>In the Pſalm we have
<list>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſiae omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um aetatum pſalmus eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligendus. <hi>Moller.</hi>
                     </note>1. <hi>Materialls</hi> of Gods Praiſe propounded in the 10. firſt verſes.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>An Exhortation</hi> to it ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, ver. 11.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Matter</hi> of praiſe here gathered up may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to two Heads,
<list>
                  <item>1. Gods gracious Preſence and Manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of himſelf in his Church, <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2.</item>
                  <item>2. His eminent Appearance for them againſt their Adverſaries, <hi>v.</hi> 3, to 11.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In the Latter he is celebrated under a double ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitude,
<list>
                  <item>1. Of a Mighty Champion, diſcomfiting the Enemies, <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4. to 8.</item>
                  <item>2. Of a Supreme Judge deciding the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel between them &amp; his people, <hi>v.</hi> 8, 9, 10.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And in his Judgement obſerve,
<list>
                  <item>1. The <hi>publickneſſe</hi> of it, <hi>It was heard from Heaven.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The <hi>Majeſty</hi> of it, <hi>It impreſt fear and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence on the earth,</hi> v. 8.</item>
                  <item>3. The <hi>Effect</hi> of it, <hi>The ſalvation of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110817:4"/> Meek on earth,</hi> v. 9. So the people of God are often called in Scripture: O that the Character were more agreeing to us in theſe dayes!</item>
                  <item>4. The <hi>End</hi> and <hi>Deſign</hi> of it expreſt in the manner of an <hi>Epiphonema,</hi> a <hi>Rhetoricall</hi> cloſure to the reſt, in the words which I have choſen, <hi>Surely the wrath of man ſhall praiſe thee,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Though the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> be uſually <hi>cauſall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Explication.</note> yet is it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times, and eſpecially in the beginning of a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, apertive onely, and little more then expletive, as <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.2. and ſo our Tranſlatours with others ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it here, <hi>Certè furor hominis, Surely the wrath of man,</hi> &amp;c. But if we read it <hi>Quoniam</hi> (as <hi>Hierom</hi> and many others do) and ſo run the ſenſe of the former part of the verſe into the latter, it may ſeem very convenient, thus, Becauſe the wrath of man ſhall praiſe thee, thou wilt reſtrain the remainder, or exceſſes of it; and ſo it makes the praiſe of God the <hi>finall cauſe</hi> of his reſtraint upon the wrath of man. However the import of the words is the ſame both wayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The wrath of man]</hi> is not ſo well underſtood in a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive ſenſe (according to the <hi>Chaldee</hi>) for the wrath of God upon Man as in the Active ſignification,<note place="margin">Vide Muſculum in locum.</note> as it notes wrath ſubjected in man, and ſo the word <hi>Man</hi> is to be limited (or extended rather) to wicked men in their wrath againſt the godly, and ſo the word <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Men</hi> is often uſed, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. <hi>Beware of men,</hi> i. e. of Wicked men. And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.19. <hi>Let not man prevail,</hi> i. e. Evil men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shall praiſe thee]</hi> It is a Tropical Expreſſion, in which the Production of the Effect is imputed to that which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110817:5"/> doth but adminiſter ſome kind of cauſe or occaſion to it [<hi>Verbum quod actum ceu effectum denotat de occaſione ejus aliquando intelligendum eſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Glaſſius.</note>] So <hi>Judas</hi> is ſaid to purchaſe a Field, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.18. becauſe he provided the Money. And <hi>Zedekiah</hi> is ſaid to burn <hi>Jeruſalem, Jer.</hi> 38.23.<note place="margin">Dignitatem tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am illuſtrabit hominum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juria. <hi>Cic. ad Lentul.</hi>
               </note> (ſee the Margin) becauſe (as our Tranſlation has it in the line) he occaſioned it to be burnt. So the wrath of Man ſhall praiſe God. That is, it ſhall afford matter for his praiſe, and occaſion men to praiſe him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The remainder of wrath]</hi> may be taken for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God that out-live the wrath of men,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> as <hi>Joel</hi> 1.4. <hi>The remainder of the Palmer worm</hi> ſignifies that which the <hi>Palmer worm</hi> hath left: ſo <hi>Iunius</hi> and others underſtand by the remainder of wrath, the godly that eſcape the wrath of wicked men. But our Engliſh Bible goes the plainer way, taking <hi>The remainder of wrath</hi> for thoſe exceſſive Eruptions of it which might redound to the diſhonour of God, or which are more then he will uſe to his praiſe: <hi>The remainder of wrath wilt thou reſtrain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Maldonat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Pontif.</note>
               <hi>Reſtrain.]</hi> The word [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] ſignifies to Gird, and is here uſed for a <hi>coercive</hi> girding, ſuch as that of <hi>Peter</hi> when he ſtretched out his hands, &amp; another girded him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 21.18. <hi>i. e.</hi> bound him as a priſoner, or tied him to the Croſs (as ſome will needs have it.) Yet they that take it for a <hi>corroborative</hi> girding, and refer it to the godly, whom the wrath of enemies leaves undeſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (as <hi>Junius</hi> and others do) in the reſult reſolve the words into the ſame ſenſe; <hi>viz.</hi> That the wrath of man ſhall by the over-ruling hand of God be made to conduce to his praiſe: and that it may do ſo, and not proceed to his diſhonour, he will reſtrain it from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110817:5"/> and confirm his people againſt it. So much for Explication.</p>
            <p>In the words thus expounded, note,
<list>
                  <item>1. The Evil Affection of men to the people of God. They are angry with them— <hi>The wrath of man.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The good Event of that Evil. <hi>It ſhall praiſe God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Gods Reſtraint upon it to that end. <hi>The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of wrath thou wilt reſtrain.</hi> —</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Of the firſt of theſe, <hi>The evil affection of men to the godly.</hi> And it gives us ground for this Doctrinall Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>That there is much fervent anger in the hearts of men againſt the people of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That I may give an account of the ſenſe of this Doctrine, and its deduction from the Text, I muſt ſpeak briefly, 1. Of the <hi>Subject</hi> of this Anger, <hi>Man.</hi> And then 2. Of the <hi>Affection</hi> it ſelf, as inherent in that Subject.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the Subject of <hi>Anger,</hi> It is <hi>Man:</hi> the heart of man is its Receptacle, there it lives and dwells: and ſo its called in the Text, <hi>The wrath of Man:</hi> which words are ſpoken,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, <hi>Inſultingly,</hi> as ſome underſtand, implying an Encouragement to the Godly, in that they are but <hi>Men</hi> that are angry with them. It is not the wrath of <hi>Almighty God,</hi> but of poor weakly Man;<note place="margin">Appellatur <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> quòd omnibus diebus vitae ſuae doleat.</note> as <hi>David</hi> prayes God to let the Enemies themſelves know that they are but Men, [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] poor <hi>ſorry man,</hi> as the word ſignifies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.20.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, The word <hi>Man</hi> is ſpoken <hi>collectively</hi> for Mankind, and ſo it implyes the vaſt number of them
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110817:6"/> that are angry with the people of God, even the whole body of Mankind. For though the godly themſelves are ſome part of Mankind, yet they are ſo few that the <hi>ſpecies</hi> is in a manner entire without them. As our Saviour tells his Diſciples, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.18. That the <hi>world will hate them.</hi> Themſelves were ſome part of the World; but alas, their number was ſo ſmall, that it made no conſiderable ſubſtraction from the totall of the world, and therefore the world is ſpoken of as whole without them, and wholly againſt them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.22. <hi>Ye ſhall be hated of all men for my names ſake.</hi> That is, almoſt all men; there will ſcarce any be found that will not hate you. What is the Sea the leſſe if you take out a few Hogſheads of water? Nothing to ſpeak of. The Vintage is counted whole though ſome gleanings of Grapes be left behind. So the wrath of man againſt the godly, is the wrath of the <hi>generality,</hi> almoſt the <hi>univerſality</hi> of men.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, The word <hi>Man</hi> is ſpoken <hi>Patronymically.</hi> In Hebrew 'tis the wrath of <hi>Adam,</hi> for the Children of <hi>Adam,</hi> the untranſplanted Branches of that old Stock. Unregenerate men are meer <hi>Adamites,</hi> and ſo <hi>metonymically Adam,</hi> as <hi>Iſraelites</hi> are called <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Look how Believers ingrafted into Chriſt are called <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. ſo unbelievers and wicked men are fitly called <hi>Adam,</hi> as thoſe that abide in him (as fallen) in his ſpirit, and in his condition. And thus the Doctrine proceeds concerning the multitude of unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and wicked men, that there is much fervent An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in their hearts againſt the people of God. Yet 'tis here to be noted,<note place="margin">Note.</note> that all wicked men do not at all times, nor all in a like manner and degree exert their anger againſt the Godly, though they all have it in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110817:6"/> them. Even the unregenerate Father againſt the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Son, and the unbelieving Son againſt the godly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.35. So much of the Subject, the hearts of men.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">Igneſcunt irae &amp; duris dolor oſſibus ardet.</note> The <hi>Affection inherent</hi> in this <hi>Subject</hi> is <hi>Much fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Anger.</hi> All Anger is hot, it's a ſoul-enflaming paſſion. The <hi>Egyptian Hieroglyphick</hi> for Anger is an heart upon a gridiron with burning coles under it. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is hot; but the Anger here ſpoken of is of the hotteſt kind. The word in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> text ſignifies properly Heat, and ſometimes the Sun for its burning heat. It notes that Anger which the <hi>Greeks</hi> call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> becauſe it heats and burns the heart: <hi>Junius</hi> tranſlates it <hi>Aeſtus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> and others <hi>furor hominis,</hi> The heat and rage of man. So it is very fervent.</p>
            <p>And there is alſo very <hi>much</hi> of it in the heart of man. In the latter part of the Text the word is in the plurall number, the <hi>remainder of wraths.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> There are heats and treaſures of Wraths in the hearts of wicked men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the godly. A ſtock of wrath that can never be ſpent up, they are alwayes angry, and alwayes ready to be more angry at them. And ſo much is alſo implyed in the word [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] which elſewhere notes <hi>abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Malac. 2.15.</note> Thus you ſee there is much hot and fiery an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in the hearts of wicked men againſt the godly. No wonder though they trade in <hi>Fire-works &amp; Sulphureous engines,</hi> when they have ſo much fire burning in their boſomes. Thus much for the ſenſe of the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and to ſhew you how 'tis ſeated in the text.</p>
            <p>For further confirmation of this point,<note place="margin">Proof.</note> ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 124.1, 2, 3. <hi>If it had not been the Lord who was on our ſide, now may Iſrael ſay, If it had not been the Lord who was on
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110817:7"/> our ſide, when men roſe up againſt us, then they had ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed us up quick when their wrath was kindled againſt us.</hi> The Church complains of the fury of enemies, that it was ſo hot and fierce, that if he that took their part had been any thing leſſe then God, they had been utterly ſwallowed up and devoured. But when was this? per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps at ſome one time when they were more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily provoked: Nay <hi>many a time</hi> (ſaies the Church, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 129.1, 2.) <hi>many a time have they afflicted me, and that from my youth up. Ab ipſis Eccleſiae Natalitiis.</hi> Ever ſince God had a Church upon Earth, wicked men have had a fire of <hi>Anger</hi> in their boſomes, ever and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non flaming out againſt it. For thy <hi>ſake we are ſlain all the day long,</hi> was the <hi>Churches complaint</hi> in <hi>David</hi>'s time, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.22. and <hi>Paul</hi> applyes it to his dayes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.36.</p>
            <p>Now there are two principall cauſes of this <hi>Anger,</hi> in which we have the <hi>reaſon</hi> of the Doctrine, I ſhall but briefly touch them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The malignity</hi> of Mans Nature. This is the Internall and Materiall Cauſe of all the Wrath which wicked men conceive againſt the Godly: the very fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell whereon this fire feeds and is maintained. And therefore is wrath juſty reckoned up among the reſt of the fruits of the fleſh in the Apoſtles Inventory, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Malice</hi> of <hi>Satan</hi> firſt againſt God, and then againſt his people, makes him an induſtrious Agent in kindling and blowing up the coles of this fire in the hearts of wicked men. As <hi>James</hi> ſayes of the tongue we may ſay of the heart of man, that in its anger a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the godly, <hi>It is ſet on fire of hell.</hi> Poets talk of fire ſtollen out of Heaven; but this fire is brought from Hell, and like the <hi>Veſtal fire</hi> alwayes kept alive by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110817:7"/> the vigilancy of the evil one. Satan has an old grudge againſt God ever ſince the day when he fettered him in chains of darkneſſe, and doth what he can againſt him and his,<note place="margin">Geſtit retalia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in populo Dei iram Dei ſibi irrogatam. <hi>Cocce jus in Nahum.</hi>
               </note> by himſelf and his Inſtruments by way of revenge, whence (as ſome think) he is called the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venger. (In <hi>Hebrew</hi> the avenger of himſelf) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.2. becauſe he loves to be retaliating upon the people of God the anger which God has executed upon him.</p>
            <p>Now there are two ſeaſons in which the wrath of men, through their own Malignity and Satans Malice, is eſpecially intended againſt the godly, times when it flames out more vehemently, as they ſay of <hi>Aetna</hi> and <hi>Veſuvius,</hi> There is alwayes fire burning in them, yet there are ſome ſpeciall times of their more vehement eruption.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, A time of <hi>Reformation</hi> in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. In 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 31. we read much of the zeal of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> and his people in deſtroying Idolatry, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring the Worſhip of God to its native purity. And then it follows in Chap. 32.1. <hi>After theſe things, and the eſtabliſhment of them, Sennacherib King of Aſſyria came and entred into Judah,</hi> &amp;c. And God takes notice of him that he came in <hi>a great rage,</hi> 2 King. 19.27. As it alſo appears by the railing of his ſervant <hi>Rabſhekah</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the walls of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> And to this Invaſion ſome learned men (as I ſaid before) think this <hi>Pſalme</hi> has a ſpeciall reſpect. I do not ſay that <hi>Reformation</hi> is alwayes the thing which immediately offends wicked men, but it is that which vexes Satan, and makes him provoke and ſtir them up againſt the people of God, and then he finds them out ſome ground or other of a quarrel, ſuch as will beſt fit their humour, and is moſt agreeing to their intereſt. <hi>Sennacherib</hi> did not make
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110817:8"/> 
               <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s Reformation the profeſſed ground of the quarrell, but his rebellion, becauſe he had withdrawn himſelf from his allegiance, and <hi>ſerved him not,</hi> Iſaiah 36.5. <hi>On whom doſt thou truſt that thou rebelleſt againſt me?</hi> As if he had ſaid, I come not againſt thee for thy Religion, nor becauſe thou haſt demoliſhed the <hi>Altars at which the people were wont to worſhip,</hi> ver. 7. But becauſe thou haſt made a defection from my So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty and Government: But that <hi>Satan</hi> (who is the generall inſtigator of Gods peoples enemies) had the greateſt ſpight againſt the King and his people for their reformation in matters of Religion, is manifeſt enough. How did the wrath of <hi>Rome</hi> burn and flame even up to Heaven in the dayes of <hi>Luther</hi>'s Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Germany!</hi> and what miſchievous plots and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices the Anger of that party hath put them upon againſt this Nation in times of Reformation, it's very well known. The <hi>Spaniſh Armado,</hi> in which that <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> acted againſt <hi>England, ad extremum virium,</hi> was formed in a time of Reformation. And the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants in that <hi>Helliſh plot,</hi> which we may now call <hi>The former Powder-Treaſon,</hi> themſelves aſſigned <hi>the Lawes of Parliament againſt Idolatry, and Seducers to it</hi> for the cauſe of that invention. Some yeares ago God put it into the heart of Authority to revive the deſign of Reformation, which for a long time before had not onely not gone forward, but receded, till we were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly drawn back almoſt into <hi>Egypt</hi> again. But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince that day, it is a wonder to ſee in what an heat the world has been againſt the people of God in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> what raging, railing, fighting, and violence have they endured from enemies at home, and from for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigners almoſt in all points of the compaſſe. We
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110817:8"/> may ſay as <hi>David, and with as eaſie an hyperbole, All Nations have compaſſed us about, and kept us in on every ſide. But in the name of the Lord we have hitherto either ſubdued or defeated them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At preſent when one of the greateſt Potentates in the world is in the height of preparation againſt us, yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and anon there is one Contrivance or other on foot in our own nation for the deſtruction of them whom God has moſt ſignally owned among us. It were an abſurdity for me (Right Honourable) to give you a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</hi> of the late horrid deſign againſt his <hi>Highneſſe</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, your <hi>ſelves</hi> next, and then thoſe for whoſe protection and government God has raiſed up him, and gathered you together. We that are at a diſtance derive our knowledge of it from your ſelves: But this obſervation among others may be very eaſily made upon it, That the grand <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Contrivers and Promoters of this and ſuch like Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems do very well know how many heads are for the preſent ſtanding on the ſhoulderrs of that one <hi>ſingle perſon,</hi> at whom they take their aim, as ſometimes <hi>Caligula</hi> wiſht all the <hi>Romans</hi> had but one neck, that he might cut off all their heads at one ſingle ſtroke.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But ſome may interpoſe; Here is indeed an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent appearance of the wrath of man in theſe attempts: But where is the</hi> Reformation? <hi>Alas, the zeal of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation is almoſt extinguiſhed among us, and it is not like the Adverſary's indignation ſhould take fire from thence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> And yet you ſee many times how great a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a little fire kindleth. It is true, the hideous <hi>Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemies,</hi> portentous Deluſions, abominable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110817:9"/> and curſed Practiſes of many among us wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to our ſhame, that pure Religion is far from that Power and Soveraignty in the Nation, which is due to it. But yet in publick Endeavours, though there has not been enough done to make us a people throughly reformed, (God onely can do that) There has been enough done to make the Adverſary angry with us as a people under ſaile towards <hi>the land of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,</hi> though we move but ſlowly by reaſon of contrary winds. The removall of an oppreſſive pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in matters of Religion, and many corrupt impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thereby enforced, under which the beſt part, the very <hi>ſoul</hi> of the Nation groned; The ejection of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſcandalous and ignorant men, from the place of the Miniſtry; The Proviſion made for encouragement of men faithfull in that work; The Redemption of the Sabbath, the Lords day, the obſervation whereof is the very pulſe by which you may make a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a peoples temper in all Religion, from profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, formerly maintained by a Law, in which there is hopes that you Honourable Senatours, will do more and more worthily then thoſe that have been in your capacity before. <hi>Nehemiah</hi> ſaies of himſelf, that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to be ſhut in the even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before the Sabbath, <hi>ch.</hi> 13. 19. I am very much per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that you might do God good ſervice in cauſing the gates of our Cities and Towns to be ſhut up in the morning after the Sabbath, I mean in <hi>removing</hi> or <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving</hi> to more diſtance, our Munday Fairs and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, in preparation for which many tradeſmen hold themſelves under a kind of neceſſity to ſteal away a great part of the Sabbath. Theſe and ſuch like things are good aſſaies to a publick reformation; and though
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110817:9"/> in ſome mens eyes they may ſeem ſmall matters, yet are they enough to make the Adverſary angry. <hi>But till the day of Gods power dawnes upon us, in which he will make us a willing people to yield our ſelves unto the Lord, and enter into his Sanctuary</hi> (as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſpeaks) The <hi>Sword</hi> and the <hi>Mace</hi> will never effect a thorough <hi>Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> A ſecond time in which the wrath of wicked men uſes eſpecially to break forth, is the time of Gods peoples exaltation in the world, when God lifts up his people among men, and ſets them high in worldly reſpects. This time comes about but ſeldome (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs) and yet oft enough for ought I know, unleſſe we had more grace to uſe it when it comes. Generally the people of God are the poor among men, trodden under foot and afflicted. Yet ſometimes it pleaſes him to turn the under ſide upwards, to ſet the poor on high, and make him families like a flock. And this ſeemes a kind of <hi>ſoloeciſme</hi> to wicked men, they think God is out of his way, and miſtaken in the courſe of his <hi>Providence</hi> (as <hi>Joſeph</hi> thought his Father <hi>Jacob</hi> was in bleſſing his two ſons) becauſe he doth not alwayes lay the right hand upon their heads. When <hi>Judah</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan a little to bear up in <hi>Aſa</hi>'s days, and had put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a military poſture, preſently comes <hi>Zera</hi> the Aethiopian with a thouſand thouſand men againſt them, 2 Chron. 14.8, 9. When the Jewes at their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from the Captivity, began to build the <hi>Temple,</hi> their enemies were angry with them, but <hi>when Sanbal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat heard that they builded the wall,</hi> that they were like to come to ſome ſtrength, and ſafety, and intereſt, <hi>he was angry, and took great indignation,</hi> Neh. 4.1. Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men think it meet that the heirs of Heaven ſhould
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110817:10"/> continue alwayes in Wardſhip here on earth, and that they ſhould be their Guardians. Like <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his ſervants they think they do very ill at any time (if they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hinder it) to let the <hi>Children of Iſrael go from ſerving them;</hi> and therefore when they ſee them go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſently they purſue them with all the force they can make. Such is their Malice againſt the Godly, that they cannot endure to ſee them in any degree of ſafety and enlargement, much leſſe of power and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in humane affairs, they never walk at eaſe but when they have the necks of Gods people to tread upon, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.23.</p>
            <p>Again, beſides this envy of the wicked at the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of the people of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That condition com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly brings ſuch temptations with it as draw the godly into many provoking ſins, and ſo he has occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on given him to let their adverſaries looſe againſt them. Yea when the godly proſper in the world, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſons that have nothing of godlineſſe in them, will be crowding in among them daily. Every one that can but make any ſhift to patch up a form of Chriſtianity, will preſently get his name lifted among the Saints, and himſelf into their fellowſhip. Theſe quickly grow light and looſe in their notions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations, and thereby taint the reſt. So the <hi>mixed multitude</hi> (as 'tis ſaid <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.4.) ſins againſt God, the Goſpel brought under reproch, and the name of God blaſphemed, and then wrath comes forth upon the <hi>whole Congregation.</hi> I remember what was repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of ſome eminent perſons that ſtaid here in the time of the war, though they were very heartily ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to the other part; when ſome that were inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate with them asked why they went not over to the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110817:10"/> quarters of their friends, They anſwered, <hi>They could do their friends more ſervice by ſtaying where they were.</hi> So wicked men do Satan more ſervice, and the people of God more hurt by being profeſſors among them, then by ſetting themſelves profeſſedly againſt them. And ſo much of the ſeaſons, when the wrath of man eſpecially breaks out againſt the people of God. I proceed now to the uſe of the point.</p>
            <p>And firſt, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>
               </label> If there be ſo much anger in the hearts of wicked men againſt the godly: This ſerves ſharply to rebuke the <hi>ſinfull Anger</hi> &amp; Animoſities of the people of God among themſelves. I know this is a beaten ſubject, but the Doctrine in hand permits me not to paſſe ſilently by it. I ſay it rebukes the ſinfull anger of Gods people, becauſe I know there is a godly kind of Anger, though I know not ſo well where to find it. Our Saviour in cenſuring him that is angry with his Brother without a cauſe, plainly implies that there is a cauſe why, and ſo a time when a man may be angry even with his Brother; and the Apoſtle commands Anger and forbids Sin in the ſame breath, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.26. <hi>Be angry and ſin not.</hi> Now we are very apt to think, that if there be any thing good in any kind, our own is of the beſt ſort; That if we are angry with our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, we have <hi>juſt cauſe</hi> to be ſo, and <hi>do well to be angry,</hi> as <hi>Jonah</hi> thought when he was angry with God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. But indeed, if the matter be ſtrictly examined, there is hardly a rarer commodity among men then <hi>good anger.</hi> We read in Scripture of many men that were angry, but ſeldome of any that were well angry.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:110817:11"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Iraſci debemus prapter contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meliam Dei, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter injuſtitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>&amp;c. Roll. in Eph.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Videndam eſt <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Non ob lanam caprinam, aut res leviculas, ſed juſtas ob cauſas; ut ſi cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Dei, ſi reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio, ſi patria, ſi parentes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> laedantur, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentur aut con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnantur. <hi>Hereb.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note>Good Anger therefore is to be attended,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ratione</hi> 1. <hi>Objecti.</hi> 2. <hi>Egreſſûs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Anger is good in reſpect of the Object, when it is excited by ſin. Sin is the proper formall Object of <hi>Anger.</hi> Gods <hi>Anger</hi> is onely at <hi>Sin,</hi> and Men for <hi>Sin,</hi> and ſo ſhould ours be: <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Be ye followers of God as dear Children, and walk in love.</hi> We ſhould ſo love our Brethren, as not to be angry with them for any thing but that which angers him. As godly Sorrow (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.9.) ſo godly Anger is [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] according to God, when a man is angry at that which diſpleaſeth God, and angry as he (though but after the manner of men) is often in Scripture ſaid to be angry. But is our <hi>Anger</hi> ſuch? Is it not evident that we are often angry with our brethren for that which we know is not ſin? And ordinarily for things in which we do but ſuppoſe them to be ſinners?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, It's common with us to be angry with our brethren for that which we know is not their ſin. Their Preferments, their Eſtates and Incomes, their Honour and Eſteem, their very Gifts and eminent A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities many times are enough to create peeviſh pangs in us againſt them: ſo our eye is evil becauſe God is good. This is like <hi>Cains</hi> anger, becauſe God ſhewed more regard to <hi>Abel</hi> then to himſelf, and (it may be) proſpered <hi>Abel</hi> in his flock more then him in his tillage. Yea, if a man doth but commend the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whom we diſlike, 'tis enough to make us angry with him too, as <hi>Saul</hi> was in a rage againſt <hi>Jonathan</hi> becauſe he ſpake good of <hi>David;</hi> and yet he is a very bad man indeed, of whom we may not truly ſpeak ſomething by way of commendation. Nay is it not a matter of Anger to us if a man doth not ſpeak as much
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110817:11"/> evil and as bitter words againſt others as we our ſelves do? men muſt reproch with us thoſe whom we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch, and revile with us thoſe whom we revile, or we ſhall be angry with them. Is this to be angry at Sin, or will you call this good Anger?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, We are often angry with our Brethren for thoſe things in which we do but ſuppoſe them to be ſinners: And this, 1. Sometimes ſuppoſing that to be ſin in them which is not: And 2. Sometimes ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them to be in that ſin in which they are not.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sometimes we are angry at that which we do but ſuppoſe to be ſin in our brethren, as their lawfull liberty, yea ſometimes their very duty. We are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at them as if they had ſinned highly againſt God, in that wherein they have not exceeded the bounds of the liberty which God allowes them. Nor (it may be) of the duty which he injoynes them. Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> was angry with the ſons of <hi>Aaron,</hi> Lev. 10.16. for not eating the Sin-offering in the holy place, as if they had ſinned beyond all defence. And yet when <hi>Aaron</hi> had plainly opened the matter to him, and ſhewed him the reaſon of it, <hi>Moſes was content,</hi> v. 19, 20. That <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> might well have been ſpared for a fitter occaſion. So the weak is angry with him that eats fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. And ſo the Jewes were offended with <hi>Peter</hi> for eating with the Gentiles, <hi>Act.</hi> 11. Though it was not his liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty onely, but his duty to do it. Of this ſort are moſt of our angry prejudices againſt our brethren in point of opinion, meer miſtakes; we think their principles cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt becauſe they do not uſe juſt our terms and noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, when upon enquiry they prove as ſound in the Faith as our ſelves; and count them diſſenters who are of the ſame mind with our ſelves, if we were but
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110817:12"/> cool enough to hear, or willing to underſtand one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. It was <hi>Theodoſius</hi> his penance injoyned by <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> for a raſh piece of cruelty, that alwayes when he condemned an offender, he ſtould ſtay thirty dayes before he executed the ſentence: And by this means upon <hi>wiſer ſecond thoughts</hi> many a mans life was ſaved. O how much of our anger might be prevented, if we would but take time to conſider the cauſe before we admit the paſſion! It's an eaſie matter to grow hot againſt a man for his opinion, his action, or practiſe which we allow not; but it is not alwayes ſo ſoon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be ſin, unleſſe we think our ſelves fit to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens Oracles, and count it neceſſary that their judgements ſhould be immediately determined by our own. But we are preſently angry at a venture, if men ſeem to vary from us. Were we as free of our <hi>purſes</hi> as we are of our <hi>paſsions,</hi> we ſhould be the moſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous people in the world. And yet if Chriſt himſelf miſreckon it not, a man had better part with many ſummes of money for nothing, then be once angry with his brother without a cauſe. <hi>He that is angry with his brother without cauſe ſhall be in danger of the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> Mat. 5.22.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Again, Sometimes we are angry with our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren for ſin when we do but vainly ſuppoſe them to be in it, or guilty of it. So <hi>Eliab</hi> was angry with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> for pride and naughtineſſe of heart, which he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed brought him to the army, and made him neglect his calling; when if he had been calm enough to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, he might have found another cauſe of his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.28, 29.</p>
            <p>Thus when we ſee men willingly undertake pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick employments, preſently we judge they are proud,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110817:12"/> and do it for honour; or covetouſneſs, and do it to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich themſelves: and this ſuppoſed pride and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe of their hearts ſuffices us for a cauſe of <hi>anger.</hi> Do we obſerve men kind and courteous to enemies? preſently we think they fall into a compliance with them. Do men carry themſelves gently and tenderly towards erroneous perſons? immediately we ſuppoſe them to be of their party. Or if we ſee a man peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably moderating between diſſenters, endeavouring to bring them to a good accord among themſelves, he is condemned as a <hi>Mongrel,</hi> an Ambodexter or a Neuter, a man that is any thing, and nothing in his principles. Thus we make men ſinners in our own conceits, and then grow angry with them, or (which I doubt is more uſuall) firſt we are angry with them, and then we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine them to be ſinners. Shall we call this a good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? Or do we well thus to be angry?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Anger is good <hi>ratione egreſſus,</hi> when it uſes good means to exert and put forth it ſelf; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, let the <hi>cauſe</hi> be what it will, the <hi>anger</hi> is naught. Good Anger expreſſes it ſelf in Chriſtian reproofs and admonitions, and makes a man vehement in perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to reformation: yea, vents it ſelf in prayers and teares for the offending party. It's ſaid of our Saviour that when he was angry with the Phariſees, he was grieved for the hardneſſe of their hearts, <hi>Mar.</hi> 9.5. And when he could not but be angry with Jeruſalem for killing the Prophets, and ſtoning them that were ſent unto it, he beheld the City and wept over it. <hi>Lu.</hi> 19.41. You that are angry with your Brethren, have you plainly admoniſhed them? or do you indeed <hi>hate them in your hearts?</hi> It's Gods own <hi>Antitheſis, Levit.</hi> 17.19. If you have not done the former, you are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110817:13"/> of the later,<note place="margin">In this ſenſe the Philoſophers words agree well to good anger, that it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Ariſt. Rhet.</hi>
               </note> and he that hates his Brother is a Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlayer. O that men would ſeriouſly conſider it! Again, have you mourned over your offending brethren, and prayed for them in relation to their ſin? If your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger be good, it will make you mourn in earneſt deſires for them with whom you are angry, that their ſin may be pardoned and removed. But do not your hearts tell you that you are angry many times for things of which you cannot for ſhame complain to God? You dare not, you dare not tell thoſe angry ſtories to God in prayer, which you will paſſionately rattle over to your friends behind the offenders back. Again, Have you uſed the propereſt means to reduce the offending party, and to gain him off from that which you conceive to be his ſin? This is to ſome pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, there is ſome <hi>wiſdome</hi> in ſuch <hi>anger.</hi> But <hi>from whence come the wars and fightings</hi> that are among pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Chriſtians? not from any pious Zeal, or good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but <hi>from your luſts that warre in your members,</hi> Jam. 4.1. What muſt we think of that <hi>Anger</hi> which ſpends (or rather feeds) it ſelf in brawlings, raylings, bitter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives, and biting language? God will not juſtifie ſuch anger, no not in <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf, though it be occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by ſin. <hi>Heare now ye rebels,</hi> ſaid the good man once in his haſte, but he had better have bit his tongue and held his peace; God gave him a ſad remembrance of it afterward. What kind of anger is that which vents it ſelf in backbitings and evil reports? What kind of Anger is it which makes men interpret the beſt and worthieſt actions of their brethren into crimes and points of naughtineſs? even ſuch as that of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> when they condemned our Saviour as a friend of <hi>Publicans</hi> and <hi>Sinners,</hi> becauſe he pitied them,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110817:13"/> and took opportunities to do them good. What kind of <hi>Anger</hi> is that which makes men deſert, yea obſtruct one another in good and neceſſary undertakings, and ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen a door to publick enemies, rather then come to an accord with their friends, though in never ſo commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable deſigns? Yea, what kind of Anger is it which engages men in ſecret Contrivances againſt their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to diſappoint them, to work them out of power and intereſt, to ſet them at variance among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſtrengthen the hand of a common enemy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and put it to the adventure whether they can ſtop the Water and ſtay the Mill when they have ground their own Grift? I doe but name theſe ugly things, each of them deſerves an hours declamation. But will you count this a <hi>good anger?</hi> 'Tis <hi>earthly, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall, devilliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee what Anger is here reproved, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all how little good anger is in the world. Now to enforce the reproof, conſider two things:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>1</label> Firſt, Conſider how uncomely a thing it is for the joynt Heirs of Heaven, and Subjects of Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome on earth, to nouriſh anger in their boſomes one againſt another. It's no marvell if the world hate the people of God, but for them to be enemies one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother is prodigious. It is objected againſt <hi>Edom</hi> as a ſhamefull thing, that when <hi>ſtrangers caſt lots upon Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> he, though a brother to the Jewes by extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>was as one of the ſtrangers,</hi> Obad. 11. Thou that art peeviſhly angry with thy brother, what an odious thing is it that when ſtrangers revile him, backbite him, practice againſt him, thou ſhouldſt be as one of them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>2</label> Secondly, Think what an <hi>imprudentiall</hi> thing it is for Chriſtians to be at variance among themſelves,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110817:14"/> when the world is ſet againſt them all. Truly it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues a very mean ſpirit in our enemies, whoever they are at this time, that they are not aſhamed to beſtow their anger on a people ſo divided among themſelves as we are, an object more proper for their ſcorn, or for their pity, if they had any good nature in them, then for their anger. Indeed there has been hitherto a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God among his poor people, holding them up above contempt, otherwiſe they are to be pitied of their friends, and ſcorned of their enemies for their childiſh diviſions. We read of <hi>ten plagues</hi> on the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> in <hi>Exodus,</hi> but there is an Eleventh elſewhere threatned, worſe then all the reſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 19.2. <hi>I will ſet the Egyptians againſt the Egyptians.</hi> If the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> be ſet againſt the <hi>Iſraelites, Chriſtians</hi> againſt <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> what can the hardeſt hearted enemie deſire more? If our enemies will but be at the charge to lay in <hi>powder,</hi> they may light their <hi>matches</hi> at our own Fires of Contention to <hi>blow us up.</hi> And doubtleſs they had done it long ere this time, if the providentiall care of God for us had not ſtrangely diſappointed them in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a probable contrivance. Yet it is ſomething to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how guilty we are of tempting men to the loſs of their lives and ruine of their families, beſides the ſin it ſelf. So <hi>divided an houſe</hi> would entice any man alive but a reall friend to overturn it. So much of the firſt uſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, This <hi>Doctrine</hi> ſerves as an Argument to perſwade all Gods people to uſe their beſt care &amp; dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to prevent the eruptions of the wrath of wicked men. Such is their fury, that if once it breaks out it knows no bounds, eſpecially in a time when the loſſe of power out of their hands, and of many high-flown hopes and ſtrong attempts to recover it, has made them
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110817:14"/> like <hi>Bears robbed of their whelps.</hi> Fire ſtraightned a while rages more furiouſly when it gets a vent.</p>
            <p>You, <hi>Honourable Senators,</hi> in the firſt place be exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to uſe the propereſt means to obſtruct the rage of Gods enemies againſt his people. You know how the wrath of man is kindled againſt us abroad, and you ſee what fire-works are ſecretly carried on at home. It's eaſie to judge whoſe hand is in them: I hope I ſhall not need uſe many words to perſwade you to do God that ſervice, your ſelves that right, and the poor family of Chriſt that favour, to lay out the power which God hath put into your hands in propelling the fury of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, that it break not out into a flame upon us, I think your coming together at this time holds ſome <hi>Analogie</hi> to that we read in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.2, 3. may it prove as happy in the event. I would not ſolicite you to any thing unrighteous in it ſelf, nor any thing really diſhonourable to the nation: but certainly it will be no grief of heart to you in time to come, to have uſed all lawfull and becoming means to guard the nation and the godly in it againſt the rage of <hi>angry</hi> men. God is my witneſſe I wiſh no evil to any man, but that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion be made for publick ſafety againſt known adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries. After ſo much experience of their malice, and ſo many warnings given us by their (hitherto abortive) Plots and Projects, can we yet confide in their ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? <hi>Sic not us Ulyſſes?</hi> But I am no Stateſman that I ſhould take upon me to propound the way of doing what I exhort you to: Be it humbly ſubmitted to your wiſdomes, as the wiſe God ſhall direct you.</p>
            <p>Next, to all that fear God I offer this exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Be perſwaded as you are Chriſtians, to uſe the beſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110817:15"/> means to ſtave off the wrath of man, <hi>And in that capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city I dare preſcribe to you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Meanes </seg>1</label> Firſt, <hi>Live holily</hi> towards God. <hi>The wicked is his ſword,</hi> Pſal. 17.13. And while you keep cloſe to him in the way of holineſſe, you may expect he will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine it to the ſcabbard. <hi>When a mans wayes pleaſe God he makes his enemies to be at peace with him,</hi> Prov. 16.7. He ſhall have enemies no doubt, but God will beat and bruiſe them down before him, till they ſhall be glad of peace: we have ſeen much of this in our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience as bad as we are; O what might we have ſeen if our wayes had been more pleaſing to God! The ſins of Gods people are encouragements to their enemies to devour them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.7. <hi>All they that found them have devoured them: Their Adverſaries ſaid, we offend not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have ſinned againſt the Lord;</hi> and when the ſins of the people of God came under their obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they think they do God ſervice in deſtroying them. It is <hi>Holineſſe (Honourable</hi> and <hi>Beloved</hi>) that I preſſe you to, not a faſhionable dreſſe in Religion, or a conjunction with men drawn up into this or that form, which is moſt in credit, but the reall ſubjection of the ſoul to the <hi>Authority</hi> and power of Godlineſſe; and this I propound as a good way to ſafety among men. <hi>Follow peace with all men and holineſſe,</hi> Heb. 12.14. Though Holineſſe will make men angry with you, yet (which may ſeem a <hi>Paradox</hi>) it is the way to overtake peace.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Meanes </seg>2</label> Secondly, Be <hi>Harmleſſe</hi> to all men. It is the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles exhortation, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Be harmleſſe as the ſons of God in the midſt of a crooked and perverſe nation.</hi> Indeed the word is <hi>Hornleſſe,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Be not like Beaſts that puſh and gore their fellows when they have got them
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110817:15"/> in a corner. Do violence to no man, though you have the ſword in your hands: Be not oppreſſive, be not injurious to the worſt of men, when it is in the power of your hand to do them hurt. <hi>David</hi> ſayes of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, They came <hi>about</hi> him like <hi>bees, Pſal.</hi> 118.12. A man may paſſe through a great ſwarm of Bees, if he goes calmly and quietly along; but if he beats and laies about him, he is like to have many ſtings in his skin quickly. A man may walk much more ſafely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong adverſaries, if he walks quietly and harmleſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them; but if he be rough and violent he ſhall find them as angry as Bees, as we uſe to ſay. <hi>David</hi> overcame <hi>Saul</hi> at laſt by ſparing him when he had him in his power, and diſarmed him by ſending him his ſpear again.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Meanes </seg>3</label> Thirdly, Be <hi>Kind</hi> to all, not onely to the good, but to the evil, that you may be like <hi>your father which is in heaven.</hi> We have a brave invitation to this duty: <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.18, 19, 20. <hi>If it be poſsible, as much as in you li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth live peaceably with all men. Dearly beloved, avenge not your ſelves,</hi> &amp;c. — <hi>If thine enemy hunger, feed him, if he thirſt give him drink, for in o doing thou ſhalt heap coles of fire on his head,</hi> that is melt him if he be ingenuous, or elſe burn him at the laſt. Chriſtians, you never had, and if you ſhould live theſe hundred years, for ought I know are never like to have a better opportunity to put this duty in practiſe then now. Many of you are full of the goods of this world, and many of your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are hungry, <hi>feed them;</hi> they want rayment, <hi>clothe them;</hi> they are reduced to extreme neceſſity, <hi>relieve them.</hi> You will ſay we have little encouragement to this, we ſee their malice is invincible. This is but a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:110817:16"/> poor objection: put on courage and charge them with love again; be not overcome with evil, but overcome evil with good. <hi>I am ſpeaking to you now as in the capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of Chriſtians onely, not of Magiſtrates.</hi> But (ſay ſome) in ſo doing we may be thought to flatter ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and to diſlike our former heartineſſe in a good cauſe againſt them. I <hi>anſwer,</hi> You have wayes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough before you to manifeſt your conſtancy and fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to your principles, if you will; but if any man will refuſe to act in good and juſt deſignes for his friends, ſuch a one may thank himſelf if he he ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and miſinterpreted in his charity to his enemies. Truly it is a very bad nature which may not be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by kindneſſe. I believe the Devil (as bad as men are) has a pretty hard taske of it to move them to violence againſt thoſe godly men that have uſed them kindly in their need.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Meanes </seg>4</label> Fourthly, <hi>Behave your ſelves wiſely towards them that are without,</hi> Coloſſ. 4.5. The Apoſtle propounds this as a way to <hi>redeem the time,</hi> that is, to redeem it from the evil of it, and make it better. A wiſe carriage among men ſerves to make the worſt of times much better to the godly then otherwiſe they would be. <hi>David</hi> makes very good ſhift to live quietly by behaving himſelf wiſely, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.5. Yea he made <hi>Saul,</hi> though his mortall enemy, afraid of him, becauſe he behaved himſelfe wiſely, <hi>ver.</hi> 15. When our Saviour ſent out his Diſciples as Sheep among Wolves, he bid them <hi>Be wiſe as Serpents and innocent as Doves.</hi> (I have ſpoke of the latter alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.) Doubtleſſe Chriſtians by their froward, rude, and unſtudied carriage towards wicked men do many times
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110817:16"/> make them much more their enemies then otherwiſe they would be.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Meanes </seg>5</label> Laſtly, Follow God with <hi>earneſt prayer</hi> for protection. This is of excellent uſe even when other means fail. <hi>David</hi> complaines of his Enemies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.4. <hi>For my love they are my adverſaries.</hi> What ſhould a man doe next in ſuch a caſe? If Love and Kindneſſe will not overcome an Adverſary, what will? But if it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures a man enemies, or makes them more his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, what can he doe then? Ile tell you (ſayes <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>) what courſe I take, <hi>I give my ſelfe to prayer.</hi> The Hebrew is ſhort and ſweet, <hi>I to prayer,</hi> That was my fefuge preſently when other helps failed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved inefficacious. Were the <hi>ſpirit of Prayer</hi> in as much vigour among us now as it was ſome yeares agoe, we might confidently expect it would as powerfully keep our adverſaries down now as it brought them down then. Theſe and ſuch like may be good meanes to keep the fire of mans wrath from breaking out into a ſlame upon us; but yet if it ſhould get an egreſſe, as I confeſſe its very like it will ere long, Chriſtians be not diſcouraged, let not your hearts be troubled. There are indeed very threatning clouds gathered over our heads, and there is much danger, unleſſe we could accord better in the means of prevention, that our Cities and Townes muſt feel the fire again ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, our Streets be waſht with blood, our Fields made fat with the bodies of the ſlain, and our ſelves and thoſe that are deareſt to us be made the ſubjects of ſuch cruelties as were lately acted upon the poore <hi>Engliſh</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>Piedmont.</hi> But I ſhould draw too many black lines upon the face of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110817:17"/> this dayes <hi>Solemnities,</hi> if I ſhould more fully ſpeak my apprehenſion of the ſtate of things. <hi>God grant us ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more Thankſgiving daies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet Chriſtians, be not terrified at the wrath of man, be it never ſo hot; it is and ſhall be ſo mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the power of God, that in all its iſſues and reſults it ſhall contribute to, and promote his praiſe. <hi>Surely the wrath of man ſhall praiſe thee.</hi> This is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thing propounded to your conſideration in the Text, and (I confeſſe) the principall Doctrine of it; but I muſt handle it very briefly, having exceeded in the former.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>The wrath of wicked men againſt the people of God is very tributary to his praiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall firſt prove it by ſome inſtances in which the wrath of man againſt the godly turns emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently to the glory of God, and then conclude in a word or two of Application.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, It puts them upon many ſubtil Devices, and cunning Stratagems, in fruſtrating of which the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God and his care of his Church is very much illuſtrated. <hi>Hamans</hi> anger made him <hi>tenter</hi> his wit and policy to contrive that wicked plot againſt the Jewes, which gave God the glorious opportunity of turning his miſchief upon his own head, and ſo came up the famous Solemnity of the dayes of <hi>Purim.</hi> Eſth. 9.20. It is an ancient practice of the people of God to keep dayes of Thankſgiving for the diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Plots againſt them; and thus we came by the opportunity of this dayes praiſes. <hi>The wrath of man makes holy-day to God.</hi> So ſome learned men tranſlate the latter part of the Text,<note n="*" place="margin">After the 70.</note> 
               <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiae
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:110817:17"/> irarum diem feſtum tibi agent.</hi> The <hi>Seventy</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The ſecret cogitation of the heart of man ſhall praiſe thee;</hi> That is, as ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it, either the enemies ſhall acknowledge, or the thing it ſelf ſhall declare, that in their moſt ſecret and ſubtil contrivances againſt God and his people, he has been too hard for them. The profoundeſt Plotters ſhall be forced to confeſs that there is no Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, nor Underſtanding, nor Counſel againſt the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, The wrath of wicked men impells them to many violent and forcible attempts upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God to deſtroy them, and ſo gives him occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to manifeſt his power in their defence. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> purſued <hi>Iſrael</hi> to the Red ſea, that they might there take a view of the <hi>Salvation of God.</hi> For this cauſe was his heart raiſed up to this bold attempt, that God might ſhew in him his power; and hence came that Rhetoricall and High-ſtrained Song of <hi>Moſes, Exo.</hi> 15.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, It makes them ſometimes fit to be his inſtruments in correcting his people, and ſo he vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicates himſelf from the ſuſpicion of being a Patron to ſin in them that are neereſt to him, and makes them that hate holineſſe promote it in his people, and them that intend them the greateſt hurt, to do them the greateſt good. Angry Adverſaries are Gods Scullions, whoſe ſervice it is to ſcour off the ruſt and ſoyle that cleaves ſometimes even to his <hi>Veſſels of Honour;</hi> and if they were not very rugged and rough-handed, they would not be ſo fit for the turn. When a marching Army is purſued or atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with a powerfull enemy, it ſerves to bring in ſtragglers, and to keep the Body cloſe together.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110817:18"/> Truly 'tis a ſad thing to conſider how farre Chriſtians range abroad from their Colours, though we have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day an allarm given us by the Adverſary. But if the Lord ſuffers their wrath to break out upon us, it will be the likelieſt way that I know to fetch us in from our extravagancies, to cure us of our pride, our wantonneſſe, our mutuall diſcontents, and ſinfull anger among our ſelves, and make us love one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother like the Diſciples of him whom we call our Maſter. If theſe ſhakings of the Rod which we may every day obſerve, prove not effectuall to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce us to a better rate of Chriſtianity, God will not alwayes ſtand at <hi>ſhall I? ſhall I?</hi> but lay it on to purpoſe, or elſe how ſhall he ſecure the honour of his own name? We pray him for his <hi>Names ſake</hi> to ſpare us: and this is our laſt Refuge we are come to, our laſt Prayer. But alas, the Argument turns head againſt us, there being a kind of neceſſity upon him to uſe ſome effectuall means to take us off from thoſe things which openly reflect diſgrace upon himſelf, and if nothing elſe will do it, this muſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, The wrath of man againſt the people of God adminiſters occaſion to him for the manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the power of his grace in upholding the ſpirits of his people, and the being of his Church in deſpight of all that enemies can do againſt them. The heartieſt perſecuters have found it eaſier to weary out them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,<note place="margin">Mal. 7.28.16.18.</note> then <hi>to wear out the Saints of the moſt High,</hi> which made thoſe brethren in cruelty, <hi>Diocleſian</hi> and <hi>Maximianus</hi> to alight from their <hi>Imperial</hi> Thrones, and betake themſelves to a private life, out of a ſullen diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content and vexation of ſpirit (as <hi>Nicephorus</hi> reports
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:110817:18"/> it) becauſe they could not extirpate the Chriſtians.<note place="margin">Plures efficimur quoties metimur à vobis; ſemen eſt Sanguis Chriſtianorum. <hi>Tert. Apol. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus Gentes.</hi>
               </note> So <hi>Papiſts</hi> oftentimes complain Rhetorically, that they find the Hereticks (as they call Reformed Chriſtians) like another <hi>Hydra,</hi> when they have taken off one head many more ſucceed it. The undaunted confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and invincible patience of the godly under per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution makes much to the glory of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, It ſerves very much to adorn Gods moſt ſignall undertakings for his people in the world. Thoſe rare pieces of Divine Providence, The Advancement of <hi>Joſeph</hi> to the Government of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> thence into the <hi>land of promiſe,</hi> the exaltation of <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Mordecai</hi> in the captivity, and reſtauration of the Jewes from it, receive their greateſt beauties and embelliſhments from the variety of Humane obſtructions through which they forced their way. Our greateſt <hi>Romancers</hi> could never yet find a more effectuall <hi>Medium</hi> to take their readers, then by leading on their ultimate deſigns through ſo many impediments, as may often make them ſeem impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible. So in all the amazing changes and revolutions which our eyes have ſeen, there is a grand deſign of God uniformly carried on for his people through an incredible variety of mens counterworkings; all which ſhall ſerve to make it the more glorious in the Iſſue. Neither muſt we expect that Satan and his inſtruments will ever leave off their ſecret plots and open oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, till the work upon the wheel be wrought off, and then it Will turn very much to the glory of the whole deſign, that men ſhall view it from the beginning in all its progreſſes, and ſee how many times through the malice of adverſaries, and otherwiſe, it has been at the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:110817:19"/> next ſtep to utter loſs and diſappointment, and yet ſtill recovered, kept alive, and brought unto perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Laſtly, It ſerves to manifeſt the glory of Gods ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice upon his peoples enemies in the day when he riſes up to avenge himſelf upon them, when he ſhall ſtand over them, laſhing them with <hi>Scorpions,</hi> and at every blow minde their former cruelties. Here, Take that for your inhumane rage againſt my people at ſuch a place, and that for your barbarous uſage of them at ſuch a time: Now ſee how good it is to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, beaten, tortured, burnt, and ſawn aſunder. Thus the enemies themſelves are oft conſtrained to acknowledge with <hi>Adoni-Bezek,</hi> the righteous hand of God upon them in the day of <hi>Inquiſition.</hi> They that ſet up the Statue of <hi>Sennacherib</hi> when his ſons had ſlain him, after his fatall expedition towards <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> compelled him, though he was dead, yet to ſpeak theſe words to all ſpectators, <hi>Whoſoever looks upon me let him learn to fear God: God is glorious in his apparell, when it is all ſtained with the gore blood of his enemies, becauſe it is the day of recompence,</hi> Iſa. 63.1, 2, 3. <hi>the day of recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences for the controverſie of Sion,</hi> Iſa. 34.8.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> But (to apply this briefly) If the wrath of wicked men againſt the godly be thus conducing to the glory of God, how juſt cauſe have we to be humbled, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering how the kindneſs of God to us has through our abuſe of it been turned to his diſhonour. The wrath of the wicked praiſes him, and his mercy to us diſgraces him. We have ſhamed the mercies of our God, and the God of our mercies, by an unworthy walking under them. You know who ſaid, when ſhe had made a <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:110817:19"/> ſhe had ſpoyled a <hi>Preacher.</hi> It may too truly be ſaid concerning us, that when we were in a low eſtate, and under the laſh, we were an humble people, a pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing people, a mutually loving people, and in a word, a people that lived like Chriſtians; but ſince we have been made free, and great, and potent in the world, we have been ſpoiled for Chriſtians, and are become a people vain and light in our minds, a people that dare boldly believe or unbelieve any thing, which will make any man vain in his converſation; A proud and haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty people, even to the juſtification of them whom God abaſed before us; Covetous, ambitious, hard-hearted, and in <hi>Religion,</hi> generally careleſſe, cold, and undetermined. Has God delivered us ſo many times, and ſaved us for this? Truly, to ſpeak after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of man, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſayes of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented him that he made man, We may ſay, God may well be aſhamed of all that he has done for us. Is it not pitty that his enemies ſhould reproch him in pointing at us, and ſay, <hi>Theſe are the Lords people?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 36.20.</note> Do you ſee them? theſe are the Saints; do you obſerve what their Religion is, and how well it teaches them? Do you ſee what 'tis to be godly? I know that in the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of Gods people, the <hi>logick</hi> of Adverſaries is ſuch, that they will infer an ell from every inch, but it is juſt matter of lamentation tous that we have given them ſo much occaſion to blaſpheme.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> But to conclude, This ſerves to perſwade Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to be patient of the wrath of enemies, though it do break out, God will make an excellent uſe of it, and preſs it into a ſubſerviency to his own glory. <hi>Let the earth be removed</hi> (if it muſt be ſo) <hi>and the mountaines
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:110817:20"/> caſt into the midſt of the ſea.</hi> Let the Saints be thruſt again into priſons and dirty dungeons; Let fire and faggots come in faſhion again, and bloody perſecutors return to their old trade; yea let that Tragedy of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edmont</hi> be acted over in <hi>England</hi> (we are too angry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelves for the moſt part, to ſee how neare theſe things are in probability upon their march towards us) But let it be as the Lord pleaſes, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it ſhall be no worſe. And though men be never ſo enraged, he will out of their greateſt fury make admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable proviſions for his own glory. And if God thinks his Glory well worth the whole charge of <hi>Creation</hi> and <hi>Providence,</hi> why ſhould not we reckon our light Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions well beſtowed upon it?</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 3. lin. 10. read <hi>Aſſertive.</hi> p. 4. marg. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, p. 7. marg. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 9. marg. r. <hi>retaliare.</hi> p. 14. l. 22. r. <hi>liſted.</hi> p. 16. marg. r. <hi>videndum.</hi> p. 19. l. 1. r. <hi>covetous.</hi> p. 25. l. 22. for <hi>O</hi> r. <hi>So.</hi> p. 30. marg. r. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.28.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:110817:20"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110817:21"/>
            <head>Saturday the <hi>21.</hi> of Februar. <hi>1656.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ORdered by the Parliament, That the Thanks of this Houſe be given to Mr. <hi>Warren</hi> for his great pains taken in his Sermon preached yeſterday before the Parliament at <hi>Margarets Weſtm.</hi> being a day ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part for publick Thankſgiving; and that he be deſired to print his Sermon, aad that he have the like privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in printing the ſame as hath been allowed to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in like caſes. And that Major General <hi>Haynes</hi> do give him the thanks of this Houſe accordingly.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Hen: Scobell</hi> Clerk of the Parliament.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
